Finding Aid for Hospice of Michigan Records, 1975-2003
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Hospice of Michigan Records 1975-2003 1982-1988
Hospice of Michigan.
04117 Bf 2
Statewide provider of comprehensive end-of-life care. The record group mainly documents the management of Ann Arbor-based Individualized Home Nursing Care. Administrative records include audits, correspondence, meeting minutes and tax returns. There are also visual materials such as VHS videotapes and photographs.
1.75 linear feet
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The records were donated to the Bentley Historical Library in 2004 by Hospice of Michigan, through Ingrid Deininger and Lois Jelneck (donor no. 9463 ).
The record group is open to research. Permission of the donor is required before publishing photographs of patients.
Individualized Home Nursing Care, an Ann Arbor-based organization, was established in 1982 by Ingrid Deininger, Lois Jelnick, and Rosemary Young. The initial mission of the organization was to provide quality care and support for the elderly, the terminally ill, and to their families. In 2002, following a merger with Hospice of Michigan, the organization became Home Care and Hospice of Michigan. The organization is Michigan's largest provider of comprehensive end-of-life care.
The records of Hospice of Michigan provide insight into the creation, management, and daily work associated with Individualized Home Nursing Care. The collection is broken into two main series: Administration and Visual Materials.
Subjects:
Hospice of Michigan.; Hospices (Terminal care)--Michigan.; Hospice care--Michigan.; Terminal care--Michigan.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Hospice of Michigan.; Hospice care--Michigan.; AIDS patients--Hospice care.; Sick persons.
Genre Terms:
Videotapes.; Photographs.
- Administration
  The Administration series is the largest series. This series includes; audits, clippings, contracts, correspondence, financial records, history, job descriptions, licensure and certification, manuals, marketing, minutes, monthly summaries, plans, proposals, publications, reports, and tax returns. The series contains documentation pertaining to the creation, finances, publicity, and management of Individualized Home Nursing Care. There is a large amount of minutes, which document board of directors, committee, sub-committee, and review committee meetings. Through the minutes the social programs, outreach planning, marketing, particular aspects of patient care and specific financial concerns are detailed. Materials of interest may include correspondence between Individualized Home Nursing Care and Yomiuri Shimbun, a Japanese newspaper, regarding the work done by Individualized Home Nursing Care. There is also information pertaining to the subsequent partnership that evolved which resulted in the United States and Japan Training Institute in Geriatric Care. The series also includes detailed information pertaining to the financial state of the organization and statistics regarding patient care, which can be found in the audit documentation, monthly summaries, and the tax information. The founding documentation within the history sub series may also be of interest because it documents the evolving goals, mission statement, and responsibilities of the organization and its board members.
  - Audits
    - August, 1998 (Box 1)
    - June, 2002 (Box 1)
  - Clippings 1981-1990 (Box 1)
  - Contracts
    - Agreement between Chelsea Community Hospital and Individualized Hospice 1992 (Box 1)
    - Agreement for Speech Language Pathology 1993 (Box 1)
    - Partnership between Individualized Hospice and Abbey Home Healthcare 1992 (Box 1)
    - Pharmacy Service Agreement with Specialized Alternative Care 1993 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence
    - Blue Cross Blue Shield 1993-2000 (Box 1)
    - Department of Social Services 1993 (Box 1)
    - Health and Human Services 1985-1993 (Box 1)
    - Internal Revenue Service 1987 (Box 1)
    - Japanese Newspaper-Yomiuri Shimbun 1986 (Box 1)
    - United States-Japan Training Institute in Geriatric Care 1992-1998 (Box 1)
  - Financial Records
    - Account Register 1984 (Box 1)
    - Miscellaneous 1982 (Box 1)
    - Mortgage Note for Individualized Home Nursing Care 1988 (Box 1)
  - History
    - Articles of Incorporation 1981, 1983 (Box 1)
    - By Laws of Advisory Board 1975, 1985 (Box 1)
    - By Laws of Board of Directors 1997 (Box 1)
    - By Laws of Individualized Care 1997 (Box 1)
    - By Laws of Individualized Home Nursing Care 1982-1993 (Box 1)
    - Creation of Domino's House Senior Citizen Activity Center 1986-1988 (Box 1)
    - Creation of Individualized Home Nursing Care 1980-1985 (Box 1)
    - Individualized Home Nursing Care Executive Summary 1986 (Box 1)
  - Job Descriptions 1988 (Box 1)
  - Licensure and Certification 1982-2000 (Box 1)
  - Manuals
    - Business File Manual 1992 (Box 1)
    - Interdisciplinary Team Medical Director Orientation Manual 1998 (Box 1)
    - Interdisciplinary Team Orientation Manual 1994 (Box 1)
  - Marketing 1996 (Box 1)
  - Minutes
    - Individualized Care Board of Directors Meeting Minutes 1993-1997, 5 folders (Box 1)
    - Individualized Home Nursing Care Advisory Board Meeting Minutes 1982-1997, 4 folders (Box 1)
    - Quality Assurance/Utilization Review Committee Meeting Minutes 1993-2003, 3 folders (Box 1)
    - Quality Improvement Program and Subcommittee Meeting Minutes 1994-1996 (Box 1)
    - Quality Improvement Program and Subcommittee Meeting Minutes 1997-2003, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Monthly Summaries 1986-1999 (Box 2)
  - Plans
    - Monitoring and Correction Activity Plan 1998-2002 (Box 2)
  - Proposals
    - Proposal for a Bereavement Program (Box 2)
    - Proposed Work Agreement with Hospice of Washtenaw 1982 (Box 2)
  - Publications
    - A Cooperative Writing Project with Domino's House 1995 (Box 2)
    - Newsletters 1990-1992 (Box 2)
    - Pamphlets (Box 2)
  - Reports
    - Financial Reports 1987-1993 (Box 2)
    - Individualized Home Nursing Care Annual Reports 1982-1984 (Box 2)
    - Quality Assurance/Utilization Review Annual Report 1994 (Box 2)
    - Quality Improvement Program Annual Reports 1994-2001, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Quality Assurance/Utilization Review Committee Annual Reports 1995-2001, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Tax Returns
    - Form 990 1984-2000, 4 folders (Box 2)
- Visual Materials
  The Visual Materials series contains a small number of photographs and three VHS videotapes. The photographs concentrate on the founding members, specifically Ingrid Deininger. While some of the photographs show Deininger with patients, the photographs relating strictly to past or current patients were not retained. The VHS videotapes focus on patient care. The video tape entitled "Home Care: Three Special Individuals, 1993" documents Deininger sitting down with two patients and the husband of a third patient to discuss what they find important in home care and how home care has helped them. The patients exhibit a great appreciation for home care and discuss how Individualized Home Nursing Care has improved their lives through assistance and support. The patients range in the condition of their health and it is obvious that the most vital commodity that home care provides is in making the last few days, weeks, or months of an individual's life more comfortable. The videotape titled "AIDS: A Family Conversation, 1993" is a conversation between members of several families that lost their sons from AIDS. The conversation is moderated by one of the Individualized Home Nursing Care nurses named Ernie Toth. The discussion of homosexuality is at the core of the conversation as is the reaction of the family members upon hearing that their sons were gay and had contracted AIDS. It is a poignant look at how families have been affected by AIDS and how parents have dealt with the loss of children to the disease. The videotape titled "Home Care Visits, 1992" follows two nurses working with Individualized Home Nursing Care through their day. The first nurse is shown with an elderly patient, she explains her responsibilities and how she assists the patient. The second nurse in the video is Ernie Toth; he is shown tending to a young male patient who has open sores on his upper body. The video is rather graphic with the camera positioned close to the patient and the open sores are shown close up at moments. The nurse is shown replacing the bandages used to cover the sores. Both of the videos highlight the types of tasks the nurses do for their patients and they illustrate the close relationship between the nurses and their patients.
  - Photographs of General Staff, 1999 (Box 2)
  - VHS Videotapes
    - Home Care Visit March 1992 (Box 2)
    - "AIDS; A Family Conversation" January 19, 1993, 58 minutes (Box 2)
    - "Home Care-Three Special Individuals December 6, 1993, 16 minutes (Box 2)